welcome to the next wasabi welded
research club uh we've had some nice
presentation about
different phases of coin joints
go into it
yeah so i'm just using this white board
here um that's
you know pretty useful for visualizing
because i feel like sometimes when you
think about these things it can be hard
to
to visualize and and here in front of me
i just have an example of what uh uh uh
how i visualize a coin join you have a
few users on the left hand side and and
they're cueing up some coins and this
arrow represents the coin join and on
the right they have a bunch of coins
that belong to different users
um
and uh the really the question that i
was trying to get at is can we
have um the wabi-sabi coinjoin process
be more
reliable and quantifiable in terms of
the expected results so how long it's
going to take
how many utxos is going to have
that type of stuff that this is sort of
what um
what i was meaning to look at and so
what i did was i just i went on this
white board and i just sort of drew drew
some some diagrams um uh thinking out
loud so to speak and and and here's what
i what i've got so far
i i thought about this problem and i
thought it would make sense to break
down the coin joining into phases um
just so so we can visualize because
really the wallet is doing at least for
us like as humans we should think of it
as three different distinct things um
the first is taking some coins um in
most cases i think it's going to be a
small number of coins right because
it's very plausible that a user will
take some money withdraw from an
exchange will want to mix it for example
and then spend it um they might only
have one coin or two coins or three
coins so we're taking some coins and
we're expanding them we're mixing them
but purposefully fanning them out
quickly so as to make many many many
coins for efficient remixing and so i've
done some some some again napkin
calculations here this is not uh
something super fancy and i said well
what if you know what if we have just
one coin right um and if we have one
coin in the first coin join we'll create
eight distinct coins from the one and so
on the bottom here i've i've written out
how many coins the user owns by doing
this
in the second coin join uh he or she
will select one of those previous coins
from the eight
and remix them again creating eight
coins from that one coin so now they
have 15 utxos
seven from the first mix eight from the
second mix
and then again coin joint three uh i i
just arbitrarily said let's just keep
taking from the first mix so you know
that doesn't nothing here has to be set
in stone um but this is what it's doing
coinjoin three now has 22 utxos and then
29 you'll notice that the number here is
plus seven every time you you mix you
consume one you produce eight cool
property of this a little idea here is
that if you had not one but two coins
then you can for example register two
coins in the beginning and in the first
coin joint again you will have consumed
two u2 xos but then still produced eight
and everything else will remain the same
same thing as if you had three coins in
fact if you had 10 coins it's arguable
that you could take the out of those 10
coins maybe take five
mix them and then in the second coin
join
select one from the eight utils that
were mixed and the remaining five that
you haven't mixed before or any
combination they're in where you end up
after four coin joins with exactly 29 uh
youtube
a question here what are the different
colors in the circles
yeah uh in this case i was just uh it's
hard because a coin joint output is also
an input right
for the next coin join so in this case i
just said like here's the user and the
this is the red coin is the selecting
coin to be spent in the coin joint to be
consumed in the coin join and then the
orange is that what they received but
then again one of the orange here is
also the one they're going to use in the
future
for coinjoin 2 to register and i i i
know it's confusing because we're
looking at like transactions kind of
melded together but you know i i think i
think this is still easy enough to kind
of visualize what's what's going on here
the user
is is just registering these red coin
and then getting
a bunch of orange and then again
registering a red coin getting a bunch
of orange it's it's sort of a fanning
out right that's what's happening it's a
fanning out okay so now what's the
result of this the result is that the um
so so yeah so a few rules right all
unmixed coins get selected um the idea
here is we don't want any unmixed coins
we want coins that are mixed
we always create eight outputs when we
make
our selection
and we always have one mixed output
selected and we stop when we hit more
than let's say 28 utxos this number is
up for debate we can discuss this but
again with this current model like if
you know adding always seven selecting
one adding adding eight always plus
seven you get 29 utxos that's just how
it works
um just just a quick uh uh obvious
addition is that in what you have there
a bit further down in the expansion
phase there should still be some
randomness right so sometimes you create
six outputs sometimes you pick two mixed
outputs you know
absolutely so like there's nothing about
this
so uh sorry what was the example you
just gave me
uh for example instead of just picking
one mixed output together with the fresh
ones we pick two or three and or
we don't always create eight sometimes
we create six or five or whatnot
so this is where i would argue it's it's
not clear if that to what extent does
that make things better for example you
can have randomness where you say
okay you know i select a coin i create
eight outputs you know and then the next
one or yeah go ahead yeah let me give a
concrete example right so um if the
behavior would always be pick one fresh
input
and and create eight mixed outputs
then an attacker knows that a single
fresh like that a fresh input on the
input side
uh is the total input sum of that user
right there's no ambiguity that there
might be a mixed one or a second oh one
sec right one sec uh no no that's
exactly where there's still randomness
that's a great point but this is where
there's still random is if the user has
two fresh coins then they could have
been together in that first coin join
but also suppose the user is in the
expansion phase and then they get a
brand new fresh coin into their wallet
it will be mixed with already partially
mixed coins in the expansion phase
yes yes but same uh same on the output
side right if we always create outputs
then assuming the attacker knows the
input sum
right for for example only just one coin
right then you know that the actual
subset
is only that which can be created out of
eight denominations on the output side
and so if you find a possible substep
with only six outputs the attacker knows
that that's invalid
and that's and that's entirely true yeah
yeah like overall if you know if you
know that let's say i'm paying you aviv
uh if i see you putting that coin into a
coin joint i already
know that it's like it's a fresh coin
and i can already conclude that at least
like eight of these outputs are gonna be
yours
maybe they end up being that amount that
i send you maybe you have multiple other
inputs
but if not
yeah yeah absolutely right so it's it's
not um
you know you can't say a few things not
just just to be clear right um
again like if someone knows
that your inputs and then
you know looks at the output size right
we are giving people add-on score based
on equal outputs right right now that's
currently the setup equal outputs don't
care if you know the input uh amount
right
so like it's it's
you're not saying that you've
you you've not taken down the privacy
lower than what we've suggested and even
what i've suggested which is having the
probability multiplier even that would
again not be broken by knowing the fact
that knowing the number of inputs that a
person has
in fact wasabi 1.0 is all about knowing
the inputs
the reason why i would go against the
idea of not doing this way so for
example like let's say you know max we
add some randomness and we say
okay we're gonna take this coin and
we're gonna create six outputs not eight
and then the next time we create eight
outputs we're actually gonna select
three coins not one what's gonna happen
is that this phase one goes from four
coin joints which is four hours right in
the best case scenario it's gonna go to
eight hours eight coin joins but what's
more important is that you know this is
just the first phase right so
the the real purpose of this is to
quickly get into the phase two which is
the efficient mixing so if i can
essentially get a user to efficient
mixing quicker then they'll be able to
do efficient mixing longer and that's
much more protection
than trying to make these
mixes perfect these are obviously the
least anonymous part of your mixing is
when the person still knows the money
because you still have fresh coins right
but i i i i appreciate the argument for
sure i i appreciate it this is
might be contentious and but there is
still randomness for sure anyone else
with the comment question
yep continue
okay so the idea is to get to efficient
mixing now what is efficient mixing well
we built this wabi-sabi you know because
it's you know it's really a powerful
tool you know it allows you to to
register multiple inputs without letting
anyone really know that you've done so
efficient mixing is using many inputs
and using many outputs if you only have
you know three inputs or you only have
three outputs there's not a lot of ways
to make a particular subset sum fit
really where you get the high numbers of
subset sum solutions is when you go
higher than eight eight nine ten but but
below six it's it's actually quite rare
that you solve this problem with many
variations so by doing
eight inputs and eight outputs on both
sides you are essentially
maximizing the purpose of
wabi-sabi you are getting the absolute
most
from the software now in this particular
case there can actually be more
variability not not not a problem at all
i think
as long as the variability does not
diverge strongly from the roughly 30
utxo limit um you can absolutely pick
six utxos create eight and then later
pick nine utxos and create eight again
or create seven to me that's i think
that's totally fine the idea here is
we're essentially like in this case i
took a simple version where you're
taking eight utils and you're creating
eight utxos and you're just remixing it
and and the the the result the end of
this this uh this thing is that you end
up with 20 u9 utxos um of which all
utxos have now been mixed a total of
three times any one utxo
has and there's a little bit of like a
tiny little asterisk where sometimes
it's it's you know a little bit more
than threesomes a little bit less
um but but on average like with almost
no real exceptions every coin has
participated in three distinct coin
joints again because they're melding
with other coins it's harder to like to
say that exactly but that's sort of what
i've sort of drawn out here so this sort
of phase two you take eight coins and
you produce a coins and again with four
coin joins you go from uh on average uh
most coins being mixed twice
now to on average most coins being mixed
three times and here again these coin
joins are much much stronger in terms of
privacy because again there's so many
inputs so many outputs and from here you
might say well how can we start to like
make more probability more kind of uh
general um expectations you could expect
for example that a coin coming out of a
coin join in wasabi 2.0 will have an
announced score on average of five you
know five seems pretty reasonable five
means there's probably like you know ten
ten people on the input side ten
distinct users i think five is pretty
reasonable some coins will have more
some coins will have less in which case
in this case you could say for example
these 29 utxos have roughly you know 15
and on score and then you can say
something about the uh and on score uh
after a number of coin joints have
happened and then sort of the last phase
which i was just sort of drawing out uh
i was i have yet
haven't drawn out just yet
would be the third phase just the
consolidation phase and in this case
we're just trying to um take these coins
and quickly consolidate them to a
reasonable number which i would say is
about 15 um coins i think that's pretty
reasonable or 16 in which case we would
select 10
produce
let's say
you know six i think is is reasonable so
that's a minus four so in order to get
that you would need i believe uh
one two three so four roughly four
transactions to do that so the
consolidation phase can be done in four
coin joints
uh-huh
yeah that's that's very interesting and
i guess the
the biggest
difference here to what we have
currently on master is that we don't
just consider the input count that we
register but also the output count so
the number of outputs that we register
um i just want to highlight that this
decreases the ambiguity of the subsets
right so assuming the attacker knows
that i am selecting eight outputs
because i am in the efficient mixing
stage yep uh for example right then the
number of possible subsets that i could
be in are only those with eight and so
here again there should be at least some
randomness uh and i'm thinking to do it
similar of how we're currently doing it
on the input side right so we we have an
input count target let's say that's
five
but then there's still some randomness
that maybe it's three maybe it's four
maybe it's five six or seven right but
the with the highest probabilities that
it's five right but it's it's still
ambiguous yeah and i think that's all
right i think the the
the the point of this exercise is to say
can we
give people rough ideas of of
expectations so if you know again the
question is like someone has a single
unmixed coin and they ask us what is the
roughly the expected time it will take i
could tell you now that if a mix
produces an atom score of roughly five
then going from phase one two and three
will always take 12 coin joints and each
coinjoin gives five so you have
or yeah each coinjoin gives five to the
participating coins so you'd have like i
believe it would be 25 add on score for
12 coin joints
to to mix and then and then the
variability is just like depending on
the number of the amount of liquidity at
the time
but that would be like roughly and then
if if it was low liquidity i would say
well the efficient mixing would have to
go a second round which is four more
coin joints to get to a mix an
additional mix for all the coins
um do you think that like having these
different behaviors across the wallet
life cycle that that is an additional
fingerprint that the attacker could use
you know if he can figure out that you
are in the efficient mixing that
decreases your anonymity set
substantially
yeah but like you have to like so
the problem there is that you have to
give um
so let's say i
yeah so
if the person knows you're in the
efficient mixing they have to find which
of the eight inputs belongs to you eight
inputs that come from previous coin
joins where there is an add-on score of
you know whatever it is five so there
are equal outputs and then the person
has to figure out which
coins you got on the right hand side
that match that exact amount with eight
outputs of which there are hundreds of
variations there so again at best you
have a probability and then this happens
four more times to me i think
you get to a point where we should be
more concerned about users
than about perfect privacy
because there are some things we could
do that makes you know like i think for
example that that's i think what is
enticing adam with these big utxo
numbers is that it's actually better for
privacy but all it takes is that all the
users have to change and like adapt to
that and then the fact that they don't
is why it's gonna be bad privacy one and
there's still uh you know the question
if if it's even
bad like if if this is actually worse
because maybe it's even not because
think of it right now like right now
there's only one phase so to say right
the client behaves the same across the
entire life cycle other than the input
selection right but i'm talking about
output selection and if we then change
that to have kind of three different
behaviors then there is arguably even a
bit more ambiguity precisely because the
the attacker does not exactly know which
input is in which phase right now
exactly but also appreciate that with
this model you're you're almost always
creating many outputs so in the
expansion and the phase two you're
creating many outputs you rarely go for
small number of outputs telling the
attacker that there's going to be many
outputs
is a shitty thing to hear even if you
say before it could have been many it
could have been few now you know it's
many i think that doesn't make it better
i think if anything it makes it worse
because it also means other people for
sure have many outputs and again if
every person on the input side has a
thousand ways they could have created
the outputs you have a really big
problem for any attacker
one thing that i really like just let's
assume that everyone is actually like
you know creating at least in an
expansion phase an efficient mixing
phase they are always creating eight
outputs and yeah uh an efficient mixing
phase for example you're choosing always
eight outputs and everything like the
point is that how many users do we
expect that we can actually have in a in
a round then
like let's say the car maximum would be
like 100 inputs or 200 inputs
that means that we're only gonna have
like 12 to what 25
uh users and all of them will have eight
inputs and eight outputs at least in
these certain paces so like it just
limits
a lot of the ambiguity and different
possibilities in my opinion
well again it's okay to have sometimes
seven you know and i would argue if
possible in the future sometimes nine i
i i don't think eight should be the hard
limit but yeah it's it's it's not a
problem to have a little bit of
ambiguity but i mean again even if i
told you that yes everyone has exactly
eight outputs and you have you know 12
users and you're staring at 100 outputs
how does that help you no it doesn't
necessarily like help me
in that case like if i know one of your
eight inputs
that might not help me too much but it
helps me a lot like if i know that
that's already like a coin that i sent
to you so it's a fresh coin so it's i
know that this coin and you're probably
gonna have x amount of other coins that
are gonna be in this like first phase
now the expansion pace that's already
giving like
i don't think so because you don't know
aviv's coin count before you made the
payment he might he might be like in the
very late stage and already in the
consolidation mode and then you send him
an additional coin yeah but
you cannot put your like non-private
coins and private coins together so like
every time you can point that well can
you
i think that you can in phase one and
two i i think in the consolidated
phase yeah it should be just price
it should be just private and and mostly
private yeah i mean like that's a point
uh so every time a new coin goes to a
coin joint i know that that's the
expansion phase and
well yeah i just think that it's like
i'm afraid that it gives a a bunch of
information for outsiders like you know
how many participants do we have in
total
how many
uh yeah
the truth is is that it is quite trivial
to give a good estimate
as to how many participants are in our
coin joints because you simply start to
you can run your own wasabi wallets you
know like from your own wasabi wallets
from your own
experience
what how you typically you know the
average number of inputs and average
number of outputs you've produced you
can you can like you can pretty
reasonably say okay this coin joint has
50 inputs and 60 outputs okay i can say
with with a a good deal of confidence
it's about 12 users plus or minus three
users right
that's actually totally fine that's not
a problem that's not a big of a deal um
as i i think you might might think
it is a privacy decrease but arguably
it's it's
very small you know considering
especially the whole privacy that we
offer yeah i do agree like it's not
necessarily a big problem in a sense but
like it's a it sounds like a decrease or
like
overall like let's say if you can say
that getting these coins private takes
you let's say for example 10 coin joint
rounds isn't that kind of like easy if
you know when the coin goes for the
first time into a coin joint you can
expect that okay like any coin joint
rounds that have some coins
you know like that where there's like 10
coin joint hops in between these two
like
i don't know like you can just draw a
lot of these like assumptions
that are really yeah i'm afraid that
these will give out a lot of information
one thing you'll notice is that you know
every person will do coinjoins at their
own pace you know some will do 12 in 12
hours some will take two days or three
days you know and and you're right like
like at the end of the day there are we
we
any smart individual will be able to say
something broadly about the wasabi user
like oh they typically put this you know
put money in you know and they wait for
this much and then they they leave like
there are going to be some average uh
case average behaviors
um across the reason why i think this
makes sense to make this more
predictable is for users right it's it's
for users it's for businesses it's for
people who
are deciding like do i have enough time
to mix my money right now before i send
it to this person
like this is gonna hopefully answer that
question and and you know to be clear
one thing that should be concerning to
anyone watching this is that if you have
point one bitcoin and you go through
this process and it takes you three
whole phases of four coin joins each
that's 12 coin joints in wasabi 1.0 it
would have taken you one coin join and
let's just be charitable and say two or
three if you want a remix to get a
certain add-on score now i definitely
think this is more private if you if you
do 12 coin joins in this in this
mechanism but we should be clear that
time wise it is taking longer and having
more randomness and uncertainty it will
only make it slower like this is this
expansion phase is the fastest possible
way
to get to the right number of coins and
then this efficient mixing is the
fastest possible way to to mix your
coins
okay uh then another question uh don't
you think it matters like what are the
size of the like them the values of the
utxos
or in other words what should trigger
the
or no sorry i have a different point
roughest point first yes you're just
just thinking like if you have like
let's say five uh hundred thousand
satoshis or if you have like 100
bitcoins should the wallet behave in the
same way more or less
no i think that there should be a cutoff
point that could even be in the
coordinator like the coordinator can
just declare the current safe upper
limit for a utxo which could be for
example today it's like 0.5 btc let's
say and so if you find out that that's
the current safest upper limit for
mixing your btc then my guess is that
the expansion size would go from 29
utxos to whatever number like multiplier
of that so if you have five bitcoin it
would be
more than 29.86 it could be a lot more
it could be it could default to maybe
maybe yeah like like this could be this
could be like a multiplier effect so
yeah it would be if if you have 10 times
the minimum then yeah i mean i hate to
say it but it could be
10 times that
another question what triggers the
different phases is it coincount is it
anon score is it a mix of both yeah it's
coin count and the fact that all the
coins are at least mixed once
the add-on score uh is gonna be
modest because you have on average two
mixes per coin once you finish the
expansion phase
so i mean if if people set their add on
score to five it might be done by then
like you might not need but here's
another thing right if if if the
expansion phase doesn't need to like if
there's no so efficient mixing phase is
is when you have coins you have the
right number the optimal number which is
again something like 30 coins uh they
need to be mixed further that's what
triggers the efficient mixing
um is that the the anode score is too
low um so it could be that okay even
but even if you have a low and on score
targets you don't only want to expand
right you you also want to consolidate
right even if it's
yeah even if you have low and on score
even if you have low ion score you don't
want to always expand you want to
consolidate yes so you'd go from phase
one to phase three
yeah yeah that's
true and rafi one thing that you should
note is that currently a lot of the coin
joins that i observe at least on test
net consume you know a couple of coins
and then create you know five outputs if
if there's a lot of users behaving like
that
it means the subset sum problem is
pretty trivial defined the subset sum
problem when you have um
not that many users and and
and just you know five inputs or five
outputs becomes easier to solve i think
it is is to everyone's benefit to have
users have a higher number of of um yeah
and that's actually what i was saying
earlier like maybe adding these phases
is a privacy benefit right because right
now there is an average user right and
that that's pretty close to every user
but if we have these different phases uh
then the average is all of a sudden very
different uh from from the edges right
because the average is still going to be
five outputs but many create one many
create eight right
right
yeah i think this can be done without
serious privacy drawbacks consolidation
phase is a minus four cross four sixteen
yeah exactly so that's exactly it so so
the third phase is four coin joins of
consolidation
and uh takes it subtracts your your
coins by 16. so then the real question
is how does this behave in different
circumstances and that's i think um
the real question is like how does it
behave in different circumstances so
what happens if a user has a couple of
coins they click the mix button you know
it mixes a few coins and maybe it
finishes the expansion phase and now you
have these br brand new coins show up in
the wallet what happens there because
now you have 29 utxos plus you have
these like
unmixed coins and that's an interesting
question like for example do you
um
do you efficiently mix with those
unmixed coins
um yeah i would say so
um you're just gonna have the
consolidation penalty as
you know the the weighted average so
but the the phase shouldn't change
you're going to get less and on score in
that round if you choose a fresh coin
and not a mixed coin right
yep but that doesn't matter excellent so
the idea is that the expansion phase is
only needed for wallets that have small
small utxo set because once you do the
expansion phase and then you start to
get new utxos then you're just
perpetually in the efficient mixing
stage you you already have enough inputs
you already uh you might even be in the
consolidation phase
right except in in that case um
i i guess you you you would be but uh i
i wouldn't think so because the
consolidation phase is is about taking
well well-mixed coins and trying to to
consolidate them to a very small number
of coins on the output side like yeah
but you can confuse you can take many
coins like seven mixed ones one unmixed
one you know you take the the average uh
anon score and then you just create one
or two outputs why not i was thinking it
might make sense to have the
consolidation phase only privy to
private coins it's a very good question
um
maybe coins that are at least mixed once
you know something like that like and on
score larger two but maybe that's not
even necessary you know because if we do
that we have worse performance in in
terms of block space right if we if we
do that we have worse performance terms
of block space do what again uh if we uh
if we do not include fresh coins in the
consolidation phase right we have to do
either more efficient mixing or more fan
out yeah
yeah so so here so you have 29 utexos
then you start to get a bunch of
payments and those payments put you
in the high you tick so count you know i
think with the efficient mixing there's
no there's no reason why this efficient
mixing can't take you know do some
consolidation like maybe phase two and
phase three
maybe they can be
like
almost like similar like just different
gradients of each other
because
i'm thinking it's uh we end phase two
depending on the andon score target yes
so so if the answer target is 50 the
idea is that once you have
enough coins like let's say you know 80
of your coins above that like once your
average score is like either entirely
above that or just about there
then you can start consolidating because
when you're consolidating you're also
mixing that that's why i think you know
it's worth noting you don't have to wait
until after that score or maybe that
score can be about when you consolidate
maybe that's maybe the consolidation is
just the cherry on top for privacy the
interesting thing as well is suppose you
you finish the phase three and i'll just
i'll i'll do this later we'll get this
right later but
um so then you have your your third
phase and
and the idea with the third phase is to
get your your coins down to like 15
spendable private coins
if you
do these
if you do the consolidation
and you have 15 private coins what
happens when you get brand new fresh
coins right you get brand new fresh
coins it expands the expansion then goes
to efficient mixing
efficient mixing then goes to
consolidating but here's the thing right
when you're consolidating those new
coins you should now consolidate on top
those original 15 coins that you have in
your private wallet already that have
already hit the privacy score if that
makes sense
this is also really good for privacy
because if if a person is like uh
huddling a lot of coins then um as they
get new coins into their wallet it
remixes with their other old coins and
it causes their wallet to be to
to not have coins that are just like
really really old and private so like it
continuously brings old coins into the
front which i think is a good thing
privacy wise because you don't want to
spend coins that you mixed uh once you
know a year ago and then you like spend
a bunch of them a year later because
you're pointing to like the same period
of time a year ago
i'm not sure if i'm
saying anything people can understand
but yeah yeah it's clear
i mean you should always coin join
before spending
yeah and that's what the consolidation
of new coins does is that once those new
coins are private they they get they
consolidate with your original 15 coins
some of those are selected as well
so that's that's a good thing the
problem here is that programming this
you know depends on how the code base is
right now i know the code base is
a little bit all over the place i'm not
sure if it's that different actually we
do have different phases right we have
the min input count target and the max
input count sorry max utxo count target
and that
changes how many inputs you register
right so we have this min and max coin
count target which is the trigger in
between the phases
and that's specifically like but there
are only kind of two phases right
there's uh there's expand and then
there's consolidate on the input side
right and i'm guessing the addition here
would be to take the same coin count
target uh and then apply it to filtering
out the output groups that you can
select
yeah but i'm thinking and and that's you
know me putting on my developer head but
it should be easy
you know because we we like on output
selection we generate the list of all
possible output groups and then we
randomly pick one of them right one of
the better ones um and out of this table
we should simply drop those
groups that are uh not in our output
target and the way that we get our
output target for these different phases
so i'm guessing in the expansion phase
we want to target eight outputs plus
minus randomness in the efficient mixing
uh we want to target
the same as our input target so our
input target was let's say it was five
but it's random right so let's say we
actually ended up choosing six uh then
we should take for our output count
target also five and do the randomness
so maybe it's four you know but yes
in the efficient mixing the the you
would always pick seven eight nine or
ten inputs
very very large so the target should be
eight and then with randomness but also
if you just happen to be more than 30
utxos then you can do a small
consolidation where you go with 10
inputs and eight outputs for example
you're still efficiently mixing you're
just slightly consolidating yeah but i
would do that probably like randomly
both up and down right index in the
expansion sorry in deficient mixing you
should sometimes have same number of
inputs outputs sometimes more inputs
sometimes more outputs sure just by one
or two you know yeah yeah exactly but
you you really want to have like more
than six on both inputs and outputs like
all all the time
all the time
you know like that's again like 100
probability so to say uh the thing is
even if it were 95 or 99 likely that you
have
like more than six on both uh i think
that's good enough but if if it's
sometimes in very few cases happens that
even though you're in the efficient
mixing phase you only have four inputs
three outputs um that kind of you know
intuitively feels like overall it
increases the ambiguity substantially
but yeah of course at the cost of less
efficient behavior which is what you
want to target i'm also like it's it's
tough for me to say if it does because
with four inputs three outputs there's
almost no way to
regroup your inputs or your outputs i
can i can tell you this like i've i've
stared at the um the simulation you know
for such a long time that i can tell you
that for amounts of less than five
inputs fewer than five outputs you might
as well just call it like one output sum
and just to finish um the the third
phase and the consolidation phase right
we have an input count target of 10 um
you know plus minus or just minus in
this case um and we have a output count
target of two plus minus right so
the question is can we ever have an
output
output count target of only one the
problem that i see here is that it
increases the number of loss
most likely right because your input sum
minus fees is going to be different than
just one denomination uh however here is
another idea consider to select inputs
that sum up minus fees to exactly one
denomination right so know which output
denomination you want to generate and
based on that pick some inputs but
that's quite new
that's
very hard to do
unfortunately
if you want to get an exact amount you
need to have a ton of inputs to choose
from to be able to like pinpoint exact
amounts yeah i'm not sure but we have
these low hamming weight amounts right
so they should sum up nicely um but yeah
but you have you have
10 15 20 inputs or something
yeah you have like you have like uh fees
and coin join fees you know like uh
network fees those are things that that
make it harder like yes there are low
hamming weights of course like you have
outputs that are literally two inputs
could be exactly one output but the
problem is is that you have fees on top
of that which make it no longer equal a
general rule for example you know we
could we could have like you know we
could kind of then see these the
smallest value outputs that we get as
five thousand cents and we could see
those as kind of the
total fee that we pay you know so you
put like i don't know a point one a
point two and a point four or something
plus then uh five thousand cents at the
end right and then you get uh what did i
say a point seven on the output side
yeah i mean
it it could work
yeah but i agree it's um difficult but
so like i think maybe you could confirm
but i think we can get this concept by
sticking with the utxo count targets
minimum maximum you know we expansion is
until we hit the min utxocon target uh
efficient mixing trigger ends with the
max output
target and max you fix all set target
then we just need that concept of the
output count target
yeah i think i think uh that that's
pretty it sounds like the output count
target is probably the
biggest change here
i would i would by the way i would love
to test this out so the the good news
about this is that it's it's
deterministic where you can kind of
roughly expect like 12 coin joints the
bad news is that for some users they're
going to be upset that you know it's
slower than wasabi 1.0 but the nice
thing is that for other users it'll be
much faster than wasabi 1.0 you know
users who have like two bitcoin for
example this should be way faster in
terms of by the way the um
the cut off if you think about it these
29 utxos right the cutoff should be you
have 15 utxos on the consolidation side
and if your safest utxo to mix into is
0.5 btc then my guess it should be
something like 10 times that so i think
if someone had like let's say five
bitcoin as an amount i think it would be
fine for them to do this entire system
without having more than like 29 utxos
because they would simply consolidate
into like 0.5
btc amounts
it would be a problem for people with 50
bitcoin though how often did we have
that as a user base people with that one
quite often quite often i don't know the
exact distribution but certainly a lot
yeah so if it was 50 bitcoin i would
assume everything multiplies
which means that unfortunately
everything multiplies ten fold yeah it
would it would be ten times the
expansion phase ten times the efficient
mixing maybe 140 mixes
yeah above but that's 50 billion
you know
yeah but if we have like multiple beers
with that level of money
it shouldn't take 140. yeah so probably
like a linear multiplication is too much
it should be logarithm or something that
it kind of you know flattens out well
just to be clear the only reason why
that's a problem is because of liquidity
right i'm just assuming that the
smallest amount that the user can get
while still getting some level of
privacy is like 0.5 bitcoin if that
number was one bitcoin then it would be
it would be much better
but by the way we have coordinators like
max suggested input value uh and
hopefully users do that so it will mean
that whales mix together and then whales
get a large anon score so how many how
many different coin joins are there then
there's like a whale one and then
there's a regular one or is there even
more in between i think it's powers of
ten
so under one bitcoin
over one bitcoin over table
it's like point one
i think point one one ten a hundred a
thousand
something like this and it's like every
second round is a point one
and then every other round is the the
one then a point one again then a ten
then the point one again then a hundreds
and a point one again and then a
thousand and a point one again
oh my god where where do these uh these
weird uh ideas come from for like
structuring
like who uh okay one sec so why not just
have a point one all the time and then a
ten
like because you want you want the
wheels to mix with the plebs
because whales will still break down
their amounts
to lower values
and and that lower output then gives
cover traffic for the plebs
so this this is a good thing until we
hit block space limits or transaction
limits but yeah so basically we need to
first get like big whales to mate with
each other and they will produce baby
whales and they can blend in with the
smaller yeah if only if only the whales
weren't all guys that's the problem
right
so
um
but i i'm confused so okay so the idea
is that whales are always participating
in every corn join but plebs are only
participating
no i'm sorry no this is a max suggested
input right the maximum so this means
plebs participate in every round whales
wait
and and they wait until other wheels
will join basically why
let me just understand why not just have
everyone participate with each other all
the time well because then you have a
problem that you know in round one a guy
shows up with 100 btc but he's the only
one the next biggest guy has one bitcoin
and then round two
the next whale comes with 500 btc and
but still the the second largest guy is
one bitcoin uh so if the first round
would have had a next suggested input of
one bitcoin
the the first whale would have waited
and he would have participated in the
second round with a thousand bitcoin max
suggested input well then the 100 and
the 500 btc guy are together
gotcha
i think it makes sense i kind of don't
like it that it's uh server side uh and
notice it's a suggestion it's not a
mandatory enforcement um but i believe
that current implementation clients
don't break the suggestion
exactly sure though
is it possible for everyone just to like
because there's the
there's the phase where um could it not
be the case that during input
registration after that's done
that the server tells the big input to
not participate is that plausible
um
like like maybe they just find out
i guess i mean you know a nice solution
would be that
during input registration you know which
inputs are already registered and that
is another idea to do that um but we
haven't done that so you only learn of
the inputs at output registration
so but if the server wait
the registration and then just removes
the largest ones that might actually be
better a bit more dynamic
it's a good point
sounds difficult interesting yeah so
again like the the mixing with
like a lonely whale is
somewhat solved it's it's not yet
beautifully solved but it's good enough
i would say yeah i'm okay with that
analogy
what's the analogy
i mean like whales
and yeah
oh yeah we're taking care of that the
big whales are not lonely that they can
find each other
yeah actually we're you know um quentin
coordination is a dating service exactly
exactly it's a modern day tinder oh this
is all being recorded oh i forgot
i don't think that's about to have so
much fun during research
okay well um just to be clear by the way
i'm not sure there is a
faster way to do the three fret phases
than 12 coin joints like i'm curious if
there was a faster way
maybe you could uh do the first phase
the expansion phase but you don't expand
to 29 instead you expand to just 15
utxos that only takes two coin joins and
from those 15 utxos you just keep
remixing from there right the problem is
that
it's it's um i mean i don't know maybe
maybe this isn't a problem like i'm i
don't know if i'm gonna be completely
honest i don't know to what extent um
this is a problem to just have just two
just 15 utxos you know i think it really
depends on user preferences uh and those
are uh speed cost privacy right so if
speed is your highest option
uh you will probably do like you know
three expansion and then already
consolidation if cost is your is your
preference then probably you're gonna do
the same you know so no efficient mixing
and maybe shorter expansion
consolidation phases but if privacy is
your biggest and don't care about speed
or cost then
yeah it can be longer yeah because you
could again you could cap it at 15 utxos
uh in the mixing the reason why i think
that's not particularly smart is because
when you have 29 and you remix
you can pick from different coin joints
and if all users behave that way then
you get a nice randomness of which coin
joins right um that's why it's not smart
to just stop after the first coin drink
because in theory you could stop after
first coin join and then go straight
from
you know
into remixing right and then just pick
eight and then and then
remix into eight what do you do then if
you make a payment and you get a change
output does it go through that whole
system again 12 coin join yeah that's a
great question it's the same as
receiving a new point right yeah like
that's the thing but it doesn't it
sounds
kind of cumbersome and especially yeah
but that change it's a pretty small
amount
like happened rather wait
or something that's kind of what i'm
saying right like the the anon scores
should not really
matter
like you can and should consolidate even
one anon score coins in the efficient
mixing stage and maybe even in the
consolidation
yeah i i agree with that i think in the
efficient mixing stage you can
absolutely mix it in and it'll just the
the anon square will just be spread out
across the the other seven coins but i'm
thinking like maybe we could do
something like this if there is a a
input
with one anon score right so fresh
bitcoin received or changed from a
single user payment
then do at least one expansion phase
ground which even in that expansion
phase round you you can so let's say you
have 20 mixed coins all above five and
on score and then you receive a fresh
one like you make a single expansion
round where you have the one fresh one
and let's say two of the mixed ones for
example randomly right and you create as
many outputs but then
since then all of your points are above
two and on score you go in efficient
mixing or into consolidation depending
on your unknown score yes so just to be
clear the expansion phase is only needed
when users don't have many coins right
so if users get new coins
and and uh and they already have 25
coins there's no you don't have to do
the the expansion expansion is just
because you had one coin and that's not
good for efficient mixing right you want
to have more than that the expansion is
only for when you don't have enough
coins so you're right max the idea is is
that when when you have your wallet and
you have already mixed coins and now you
have a fresh coin coming in what if
those fresh coins what if that fresh
coin was just mixed with the private
coins in an efficient mixing round
right away okay so that's oh okay so
then how about this um the expansion
phase
ends
with a utxo count target right and that
means if you have above utxocon target
and you get a fresh coin you don't
expand yeah exactly yes the the
efficient mixing phase ends with an
ammon score target right so yes um that
means
you
only consolidate coins above a certain
anon score target yes that might be
actually the way to go different
triggers yeah and the efficient mixing
right ev so if you have eight coins you
only need one coin join to remix if you
have 16 you only need two coin joints
maybe we don't need 29 coins or
essentially 32 because 32 is four times
eight right maybe we could get away with
fewer than that oh sorry your 29 is
correct uh because you you spend points
right so you destroy them and generally
yeah exactly so 29 is correct but i'm
saying like when you have let's say if
you have 32 utxos that should be the
hard limit because 32 utxos to to remix
each one a single time is four coin
joints because you have to you know you
on average you consume eight right yeah
then with a multiplier for wheels
something like that um
yeah
i don't know really interesting aviv
i've been thinking about this for a
while and you've articulated and uh
summarized it very nicely and i think
we're on to something here yeah the the
interesting thing is that what's
currently being done is
you know because i noticed this is like
for for just so many coin joints you
just have the expansion phase just goes
and goes and goes that was back in the
day i mean now it's it's it's less so
since since the latest uh code patch i
think this can be fleshed out i don't
think we have to do this now but i think
we can absolutely flush this out let me
see if i can just
do you know uh with your simulations um
so
so an arbitrary input sum
how many
output groups
of a low output count do their exist
so let's say we have to target output
count of two
how many groups do there exists roughly
on average for any input sum
output count of two like two utxos
uh yeah i know all the applicants there
aren't that many because there's only uh
43 or 46 denominations under one bitcoin
so it's just 46 times two so it's like
overwhelmingly small it's like insanely
uncommon yeah and that's that's going to
be the big problem right because that's
like saying like how many how many
different amounts of money can you make
with just two coins the answer is almost
none because most money is like 67 cents
68 cents 69 cents 70 cents 71 72 those
are all never going to be two coins
right two coins is very rare there's
like there's only like 10 different
types of bills or whatever so there's
like 100 variations but there's like
tens of thousands of of values yeah so
the question is how efficient can we get
that consolidation like how small
how long
ten to six is probably your best bet i
know for sure with eight you guaranteed
that you can get it done yeah and with
six you get most of them with 68 most of
them but because you you have different
inputs you can choose from
you have some ability to pick the ideal
input so that you can consolidate it
down to six but yes six is probably your
best bet but six isn't even that much of
a consolidation it's still intended to
create a bunch of coins yeah it's it's
not but i mean
again that's why i don't recommend you
know blowing up to like 50 utxos
one thing that we did for
uh
input selection or output selection i
think it was input selection i by now
the code has changed but what we did was
you sort the so in our example with
output selection now how we would do it
you generate all possible output groups
right and now you sort them by output
count as sending so you start with the
group that gives you one output there
might be one or two groups like that
then you have the two output groups
three output groups the four output
groups and then you take a random walk
from the top to the bottom right so
there is a 50 chance you take the first
one if you flip the coin and it's true
you pick the first one right if it's
false you continue to the next item and
you throw the coin again
right and if it's false you pick the
next one if it's false you pick the next
one
and then eventually you hit true right
so the largest probability is at the top
of the list i think something like this
might be suitable here again
uh yeah that that's
uh for consolidation phase yeah you can
do
you can have some randomness i'm gonna
tell you now that you're not gonna have
a couple of options that are in the two
coins i think i think um but there are
gonna be some right so there's probably
not gonna be any of one there's gonna be
some with two more with three more with
four a lot with five a lot of six very
many of seven and eight right
yes so when i was doing the calculations
for exact amounts typically you don't
get any
options until you hit about eight if you
give if you give yourself a range of a
thousand satoshis you get a few in the
sixes a few in the sevens a lot in the
eights
yeah but we do accept the loss
i'm not sure where we stopped i think no
no that's okay three times the the
lowest loss out of all so we generate
all possible output groups and right now
we like we take the one like we order
the list by uh loss
ascending
uh and we we fill the table
so the that output group with the least
amount of loss and then
until that output group with 1.3 times
the loss of the very first one right and
out of that
short table list we pick randomly right
not a random walk a random pick that's
fine i'm just i'm just telling you that
um like the entire point of the
simulations for me was to get a grasp on
probabilities and different permutations
ways you could build things and i was
surprised when i found out that like
those those really only occur when you
have
larger number of outputs it's quite rare
for a smaller number
but yeah that that's fine yeah you're
saying you want to make the
consolidation phase more efficient by
consolidating to a smaller number i'm
i'm 100 for it i just think that it's
only going to be reliable down to six
utxos that's like that's like what
you're going to guarantee
sometimes maybe you'll get five there is
if there is an output group with four
coins that still has a small enough loss
then we should prefer that one totally
yeah
so basically the algorithm would be
generate all possible output groups
um sort them by loss
shorten the list down to that output
group with 1.3 times the smallest then
again reorder that
table
based on output count and then take a
random walk right so
first we generate all possible output
groups then we remove all those output
groups so that first list might have
a two groups like two output groups you
know but that two output group has
two times as much loss as the smallest
one so in the second step where we
remove the high loss uh output groups
those like that those very low output
current groups would likely going to be
removed
and then out of that shorter list we try
to random walk
from the top based on utxo count
yeah that that could work yeah is it is
it plausible this gets in before release
if you make a pr
yeah um i guess we have to see of how
bad the current master branch is right
so i'm i reset my wallets by the way and
i'm starting from one coin one anon
score and like you think 18 wallets or
something uh i will see how it behaves
um
and
yeah you see
okay
makes sense
max are you running like multiple
wallets or multiple clients
multiple clients have eight clients and
they have between
two and three wallets and one of them
has
six wallets i think
the beauty of cubes and virtual machines
[Music]
do you have your laptop reassigned
yeah do you have any like clients that
that there are like there is only one
okay one wallet
uh i had uh but then i
didn't
i added more wallets just to get more
wallets so no but that's probably a good
idea i should probably do it why not
yeah probably you should because that's
how maybe most people would use their
their wallet you know
and i do believe that i don't know this
unknown score calculation when you are
running multiple wallets is kind of
either broken or something is wrong you
know
i had like think
so like i think it makes sense because
so you have a coinjoin round you have
two wallets in the same client that
participate in that coinjoin round and
now these two
wallets
get into the same denomination group
right you
know that they belong to you
both of them and therefore we don't
increase the anon score count like with
those same client utxos same client
different wallet utxos yeah yeah yeah
pro that's probably right but my point
is like more from the ux point of view i
had like three wallets running and they
were all coin joining two of them like
got 100
private you know that uh lev progress
level and the other one no so okay i had
like you know they were all coin joining
but then three of them participated in
the next coinjoin round you know and
then then the uh the the the the privacy
uh progress in the two wallets that
reached 100 already now decreased you
know so it's uh it's completely uh
in my opinion it's broken i don't think
that should happen anymore because of
the weighted and on score it happened
with the master with the recent monster
on maintenance yeah interesting
uh i i think the
so that's a ux problem another ux
problem is
you have two wallets in a client and now
you switch laptops or switch clients and
uh now you only load one of those two
wallets
and you make a rescan and you calculate
your add-on score from scratch uh it
will be a different result on the two
laptops and yeah exactly yeah that's
what i'm talking about as well
yeah it's this is like one of those
things where you want to be conservative
right and
uh that's why we consider same
client
wallets you know it's it's like if you
have
uh in the same wallet so one wallet in
one client
um and you get two coins in the same
denomination
uh we we also don't increase the ammon
score count
right
yeah i get i get that but my point is it
would be it would be good if you have
like
yeah it would be good if you have one
client that has only one wallet or two
you know just to
because basically that's how most users
would use the 2.0 also but you know i
also increased my anon score targets uh
to a thousand plus
so i i'm not really testing
user behavior i'm just testing
production graph kind of
maybe to switch the topic or do you guys
have something more about the
consolidation phases
no i'm just thinking of like
consolidating now my all my coins in
different wallets
this is annoying our sending
process like requires many yeah many
windows and many things that you have to
be typing but yeah that's what i have
been telling
yeah i mean like especially now that you
have to do multiple payments in a row
like this is annoying this should be
like so much easier like why can't i
just there
yeah there should be like a i believe
there should be a wallet title where
that has two like two boxes right a
mountain address and you paste it there
and it just jumps to transaction preview
well no it doesn't have labels i think
overall we should just have like you
know at least uh from inside a wallet
when when you want to make multiple
payments in road from one wallet we
should enable you know
creating multiple outputs
yeah but it's many is
well it's implemented in the rpc server
but was never in the gui 1.0 and
but i think that would be really
convenient if this wallet is designed to
be an actual wallet that people use for
private payments
we should not make them do every payment
one by one yeah but just notice that uh
i'll pay too many is quote bad for
privacy because the two recipients can
like see that there is three outputs in
this transaction right so you can only
do pay too many if you are comfortable
to reveal the two payment destinations
to the other person or if you do very
but isn't that maybe good for privacy
because if there is only two outputs
then the recipient knows that that's for
sure your utxo so maybe that's good for
privacy no but you see pay too many will
usually give you three outputs right you
have two payment destinations and your
change
and then when you have three outputs
that's what i'm talking about right yeah
but
any of the recipients wouldn't know that
which utxo is yours
ah
okay i see
well counter argument if you make two
payment outputs with rounded amounts you
get a non-rounded change well that's
kind of another issue but yeah yeah but
my point is if you have more outputs
yeah moving on slightly different topic
old idea but i think still worth talking
uh about and that is a thing i call the
likelihood to coinjoin right so before
input registration you throw a coin and
if it hits true you participate in this
current round of coinjoin if it hits
false you do not participate in the
current round of conjoint uh the the
weighting or the probability of that
coin should depend on user preferences
so if you are in speed
priority your you should uh have like a
probability of 95
to participate in this next coin join uh
if you have a privacy priority
you should participate only in i don't
know like 50 of of the coin joints or
something like that one of the nice
benefits is that we will have even fewer
same transaction uh remixes
because right now in input selection of
a single client we already prefer not to
have same transaction remixes right so
to remix two coins that you got in the
same previous coin chain transaction
however because every user mixes every
round 100 of the time as soon as they're
online in autocoin join us on that that
means that there is still a rather high
number of same output uh same
transaction remixes uh which then we can
say would rather high likelihood they
are from different users
this is a great example of a good
privacy feature but another feature that
just kind of goes against users having a
good understanding of
what's going on and good expectations of
how long things are going to take well
you could take that the weighting of the
of that coin
and consider it in the
in your time estimate right so let's say
the privacy preference has a 50 chance
you expect that you need 12 rounds of
coin join uh and so you multiply that by
point by two and so you know in 24
rounds you're gonna be done
okay but users are gonna hate that like
users are not gonna love the idea that
their software is flipping a coin of
whether or not to like participate
uh
yeah users
but that's the user preference right if
the user wants speed be as quick as
possible i still think there should be a
non-hundred percent probability like it
should be very small or there already is
there already is another 100 probability
when i when i go on testa and i run my
thing i never i rarely
am able to just go and and and
participate in 24 coin joins in a row
it's almost never i'm always something
happens i have to close my laptop or
whatever like things change
yeah but that's
that's another thing right then if you
uh like if if we don't have an active
probability like that then
when a coin stops mixing we can kind of
assume the user went offline right
because that's the only case where it
happens or it reached the amount amounts
of target
but if there is such a probability and
coins don't mix well might as well be
that the user is still online
but he chose not to mix right now
i mean i i get i get the idea i i back
it up in terms of that it's good for
privacy i think it's one of those ideas
that um we can have it as a toggle for
users for sure if if they want that as a
toggle and if they don't have a lot of
constraints and they want the best
absolute best privacy result but i'm
guessing for the for the middle of the
of the line user users are going to want
efficiency and cost
uh low time low cost i mean we we can't
assume that like there are users
who are privacy extremists right who are
like i don't care how long it takes so
much it costs give me as much privacy as
possible and then there are users who
are like hey i need to spend this in
like an hour so i need to be done quick
you you also have to appreciate that a
big part of the money that's going to
come into the company is going to be
people like businesses who who see a
business case where it's not just like
personal funds but actually like a
volume of funds in order to like protect
business privacy right i mean um for
example
our company not that we're doing this
now but well actually we are doing this
now so like we sell gift cards for
bitcoin right and so for us it's like we
don't really have a time constraint
not not that much um but it would be
good to know that stuff wraps up in like
a like a day or two and that it's like
efficient cost wise so that it's not
like a huge part of the amount of money
the nice thing with wasabi 2.0 is that
this would only work in 2.0 this is like
literally does not work in 1.0 because
gift card amounts are like
all over the place
yeah
but can we drill down more like is this
actually a benefit for privacy that
sometimes clients skip around
yeah any time you you add some
uncertainty for sure it's a benefit for
privacy the question is is that does
that is that a reasonable attack vector
that someone could exploit that they
know that a user is likely to engage in
coin joins one after the other i would
say yeah
like it seems to me that if you
increase the number of potential coin
joint transactions that are relevant you
increase ambiguity by a lot maybe
exponentially i don't know but at least
by a lot yeah but i i just i would not
you know just knowing from my own
personal experience how
plausible it is for
not being able to participate in in in
enough coin joins i can
you know tote like even say you're
following someone's coin and it's a
large coin and then you follow it and
you think you know kind of which outputs
it might be and then you know what if
that user has other coins that he's
mixing and so now he's just selecting a
different set of coins so now those
coins are mixing in like off
you know they're not mixing sequentially
they're mixing like sporadically
yes
you can get infinite there's an infinite
way to approach privacy yeah so so so
yeah so right now my goal is is to keep
the privacy and and to make it more user
friendly and like like more workhorse
kind of because i think the privacy we
have is enough my my concern is that out
of the gate we're going to have users
complaining
one doesn't matter what the video is
going to happen
people complaining but yeah no no i
don't care about there's a very
difference i don't care about people
saying random on twitter i care
about actual people complaining like i'm
using the wallet and then this isn't
working for me that's the only complaint
that matters
and you know a counter argument against
my point is that there are already
some times where we do not mix for
example uh the whale rounds right so if
you're a whale you're not gonna
participate another example is the
median uh transaction fee but whale
rounds are known one sec whale rounds
are known uh yes right but so so let's
assume two things right let's assume
you're a whale you have 100 bitcoin
input so you're not going to participate
in
max input below 100. and additionally if
you set the median transaction fee
window to like months it means you're
not going to participate if the current
fee rate is larger than the median of
the free rate of the last month and then
both of that together means that you're
not gonna
even if there is a whale around if the
current fee rate is too high you're not
going to participate right and now if
you would add a third thing there it
might be that we are in a whale round
and even though the current fee rate is
low you might still flip a coin and it
says don't coinjoin and then you have to
wait until the next whale round that is
with a low fee
i just so badly don't want to be
debugging someone's wallet and then it's
like oh by the way there's a chance in
the logs it'll say that you flipped a
coin and that's why you didn't
participate you know what i mean like i
i think we have enough
it's it's just it's not a bad idea it's
just that it's the the question is is it
it's a marginal cost right like marginal
cost marginal return are we getting a
lot of privacy from this is the user
going to appreciate that they're getting
a lot of privacy and what does it cost
the cost is that we're going to have
users have sporadic behavior and it's
going to slow down their process even if
it's slowing it down 20 percent like
right now it's clear that our software
with the design decisions we've made
seems like most users are going to have
to spend overnight like mixing their
their wallet to get the their money
slowing things down seems like a like a
concern
yeah i agree that for some users it's
going to be important but again then for
that user group that prioritizes speed
the probability of not mixing is super
small so then it doesn't really matter
right but
if if your priority is privacy then sure
why not take your time and the cool
thing is that improves the privacy of
those even of the guys who want speed
and because they're not gonna remix with
your coin of the same previous
transaction
i see
yeah i see what you're saying i see the
benefit of purposefully mixing at
different time periods right which is
almost like what you're saying yeah that
would be another thing for example kind
of like fake
a different time zone something like
this only even though my computer is
running 24 7 like i'm in america but
only makes during chinese data for
example yeah
i see what you're saying so what should
we call this feature pretend to be
chinese feature i think that would that
would work well with the
lurking wife mode
[Laughter]
welcome to wasabi
yeah i i was thinking more that you mix
on a tuesday and then you say you know
what i'm gonna wait and then i'm gonna
mix again on a thursday and i'm doing
this because i'm mixing with a different
group of people now so rather than
mixing you know hundreds and hundreds of
times wasting tons of money and you know
i'm gonna mix at a later time this is
kind of like your idea of skipping
transactions although this is more you
know explicitly like this would be like
skipping days you know at a time yeah
users kind of behave like this a little
bit like i i can imagine a lot of users
you know mixing sometime and then
stopping for some some period and then
mixing later but the the bigger the
bigger question is how at risk are these
coins of being detected you know that's
the really the big risk how at risk are
these because the protection of these
coins is so much greater than wasabi 1.0
ah yeah but it's
so tough right we need like so difficult
to quantify what's the privacy we
actually give and what's actually enough
you know but 2.0 seems like such a
massive privacy that it's probably
enough you know and at this point we can
improve uh fee and and speed and ux has
anyone done
has anyone done a large transaction yet
have we seen any
what uh you mean with many inputs many
outputs yeah like 200 inputs 200 outputs
uh yeah i would love to use for someone
to get all the coin joint test
transactions and order them by output
count uh nobody has done that so far um
i think i have okay order them by output
count
do you have an up-to-date list of all
the conjoined transactions on tesla yes
i do
cool
how do you get it um
i used um
uh block
explorer and then i i essentially
filtered for a bunch of things
cool
so you kind of rebuild dumplings for 2.0
um i didn't have to write much yeah
yeah and then sometimes it's unclear
like if i've actually hit one but i
don't see anything over like let's see
here one sec i think the largest i saw
was something like 153 i remember
inputs um
yeah i see a lot of large stuff recently
but i can't are these
coin join
dude i swear to god is there another
person running a test net coordinator uh
i believe yes but i'm not 100 certain
yeah because there are some coin joints
that don't exactly look
like wasabi like yeah but by the way
then you don't oh well no actually you
would but you would need to change the
client mainly for that right but run a
different coordinator so that only your
uh configured client is there
yeah
let me send this transaction what do you
guys think of this who does this belong
to can you share the screen looks
suspiciously similar let me share my
screen window transactions
looks a little suspicious uh looks a
little bit uh looks like something
something naughty is happening here but
is that even an amount that is right
eight three eight
i know these are amounts and then three
i know this is an amount for sure that
looks like 2.0
so this one here has um
192 inputs 197 outputs that's the
biggest one i have 192 inputs and
outputs that's pretty cool
yeah 190 on both sides yeah almost 200.
that's pretty nice and it was a pretty
big consolidation transaction as well
and when did it happen
oh no i was wrong it's not consolidation
training at all it happened really
recently
uh oh five twenty seven three days ago
well that's weird because like yeah
there was probably just one adam and max
testing test that everyone else wasn't
doing other things
yep sounds about right
what about this one matches this one
looks like it right
this one has
188 and 206
nice
which is pretty good the the the the
goal is we i wanted to see like
coin joins where
you know i knew that there could have
been 30 people in it because that's what
we're going to expect right when we
launch this
we expect that at any moment it is
reasonable to assume that 30 people are
going to be mixing and when you have 100
inputs hundred outputs it's unlikely
you're going to have 30 people
i can tell that so many denominations
are skipped is is is this do you think
this was before the the whole frequency
table was was dropped 05 27
wait is the frequency table dropped
is it i don't think so
okay because unless that's real shame
that's a real shame i i think the
frequency table is a real bad idea
yeah i came to agree um but again like
having
equal amounts
seems like a more
uh conservative approach but again only
if you do not consider the knapsack
multiplier so
yeah i get your point i'm almost
convinced that it would be better to
remove it one cool thing that if we
remove it it would be easier to select
inputs um that are right
close to the value that you want right
oh it's not just a little bit easier
it's a
hell of a lot easier i think there's
only like 20 different denominations
here i think it's quite narrow in terms
of how many denominations i see here
yeah that's frequency table
aviv do you think you could
handle the code for removing the
frequency table i i i shouldn't be even
if it was simple it still wouldn't be
right for me to do that i i i would 100
be down to go with with adam and do some
paired programming and i'd even be happy
to do it but i i would need supervision
yeah i think if you can do
a couple pair programming sessions with
adam and
get some concrete
improvements in code like improvements
that you're convinced on a theoretical
level but where adam has is uncertainty
what schedule is going to be so let's
schedule it let's uh we already have a
few we have uh some for uh output
selection we have um yeah we have a few
things anyway so let's let's let's do it
i can i can book some time without him
yeah please do adam is probably the best
to do the pair programming with uh he's
quite deep into that code
but he's very tired of it
let me just find his
poundley again oh yes uh we actually
never uh finished up my previous
question of what were the changes that
you did in the last pair programming
session it was just um
no i mean we just told it previously so
when you have more than 21 private utxos
you consolidate them to less than 21.
but that's just changing the utx account
target
then was that the only change you did
just changing that
one configuration value i think so
i see
okay book some time for him tomorrow
pretty early in the morning for me cool
let me know the time i'll try to join
okay
we talked about the
output
selection strategy with different phases
we talked about likelihood to coin join
is there any anything else
nope that's
that's the most important stuff for now
anything yes
nope i'm gonna go get some breakfast and
a coffee well deserved
yeah great then i'll stop the recording
thanks everyone for joining this week's
wasabi research club
see you on the next one